UTU Memorabilia 5139 MB
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
UTU Memorabilia
1926-1983
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
United Transportation Union (UTU)
5139 MB
1.61 cubic feet
1.6 linear ft.
Memorabilia.
UTU memorabilia including comic books, membership cards, buttons, key chains, literature, and many other miscellaneous items
5920148
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 01, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The United Transportation Union (UTU) is headquartered in Cleveland, Ohio. It is a broad-based, transportation labor union representing about 125,000 active and retired railroad, bus, mass transit, and airline workers in the United States.
In 1968 four brotherhoods' became interested in joining together to make one transporatation union, the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen and the Switchmen's Union of North America. The new union was to be called the United Transportation Union and came into existence on January 1, 1969, after an overwhelming vote of the 4 unions on December 10, 1968, in Chicago.
The first president was Charles Luna, formerly president of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and had 230,000 members. The International Association of Railway Employees joined in 1970. The Railroad Yardmasters of America joined the union in 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5139: UTU Records 5139 AV: UTU Audio-Visual Material 5139 P: UTU Photographs 6055: UTU Additional Collective Bargaining Agreements 6023: UTU Additional Records 5164: UTU Canada Records 5622: UTU New York State Legislative Board Selected Files 5711: UTU New York State Legislative Director Files 5589: UTU Vice-President's Office George W. Legg Subject Files 5501 AV: UTU. Young Leadership Conference Audio recordings 5196: UTU Ladies' Auxiliary Iowa Joint Board Minutes
United Transportation Union; United Transportation Union --- Collectibles
5920148
- H.E. Gilbert's gavel (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Wooden gavel, with engraved gold plate "H.E. Gilbert"
- "Cliff Merritt - Sets the Record Straight" comic book (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Comic book that depicts a member of UTU and how he deals with a family situation.
- UTU membership cards, 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Membership cards for 'voluntarily contributed or pledged at least $100 to TPEL, the voluntary political arm of the UTU". And a card that states "D.W. Collins has been duly elected to represent the International Union in the capacity of Asst. General Secre
- Golden Spike Centennial booklet, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This is a folder "The Golden Spike: A Monument to American Labor" with a "Centennial Statement of Charles Luna, UTU President" included inside. Also included a "Golden Spike Centennial Issue" of "Transportation News".
- UTU - bumper stickers and emblem (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Emblem - oval - black lettering "UTU"; bumper stickers - "We believe in the American Rail Way"; "Keep on Truckin'By Train UTU"
- UTU - stickers, patches, key chain (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Stickers: black with white lettering "Your Right to Drink Ends When my Shift Begins" "Operation RedBlock"; patches: white w/black trim and lettering "Operation RedBlock"; key chain: white w/gold lettering "United Trans. Union, F.B. Boardman"
- UTU - Pocket protector, coin holder, letter opener (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Letter opener - gold & black with gold lettering "United Trans. Union F.B. Boardman" with a black leather case; coin purses - black with white lettering "UTU Insurance Association"; pocket protector - blue with white flap "United Transportation Union, P
- UTU - buttons, key chains, souvenir coin [booklet on coin included], 1969-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Souvenir coin - gold with raised picture and lettering "Progress Through Unity, January 1969" [side one]; "United Transportation Union" [side two]; buttons - "I Support Operation RedBlock"; "I Give TPEL Do You"; "UTU Supports Operation RedBlock"; "It
- UTU - buttons, push-pin (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Push-pin - gold plated miniature replica of a railroad spike in honor of "Golden Spike, Centennial" [also included is a card about the Centennial]; "UTU"; buttons - "UTU, Progress Thru Unity, One for All, All for One"; "Trains Are Safer, Les Trains So
- Copper Tie Tack, from service on the C&O-B&O Clifton Forge Division in Augusta County, Virginia, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Railroad Tie Tack, copper, with the no. "26" engraved on head. See enclosed letter from D.W. Collins for full description (too long to include here)
- UTU - Buttons (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Buttons - "Ask Me Why I Am Negative, Operation RedBlock"; ""UTU, It Doesn't Cost To Belong, It Pays"; "Save The Caboose, UTU, Saves Lives"
- UTU - Push-pins (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Buttons - "UTU" some commemorate years of service - 10, 20, 30, 40, 45, 55, 60, 65, 70
- UTU - Campaign buttons, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Buttons - "It's Hardin for Me in '83"; "UTU 'Loves' New York"; "J.F. Collins, Vice President, UTU '83"; "Canadians for President. Hardin"
- UTU - buttons, push-pins, commemorative coin (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Push-pins - oval "UTU"; buttons - "It Doesn't Cost to Belong It Pays UTU"; "Buy American - Union Made; "Ton Mile Tax Thru UTU"; push-pin shaped like New York State with "UTU" in center; souvenir coin, gold with raised pics of Luna, Lane, Spers, & Gil
- Dan Collins' convention badge, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Name badge for Dan Collins from the "4th UTU Convention, Miami Beach, Fla., 1983"; Canadian push-pin attached; rope tie and tie tack bronze with lettering "United Transportation Union, 4th Convention, Miami Beach, Fla, 1983" with an "UTU" symbol in the
- Two audio tapes [originals] converted into two audio cassettes. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  One tape has songs on it, sound and audio is not great, they are work songs from what can be heard. Second tape is a dedication of a train, again the audio is bad, and the background noise overpowers the voice at times. Sound of train whistles in the back
- Assorted Buttons - removed from collection 5139, see in notes for more specific information (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Buttons - Join SU of NA; UTU, Progress Thru Unity; Save the Caboose, Save Lives, UTU (box 54); Let Conrail be Conrail; Supports Operation Red Block; UTU, Progress Thru Unity; Join SU of NA; We Like Our Independence, VOTE SU of NA (box 54); As me a
- R.G. (Ron) Hughes - campaign post card (Box 2, Folder 2)
  removed from 5139/box 53
- Daniel Collins - membership cards (Box 2, Folder 3)
  removed from 5139/box 58
- By-laws of Buffalo District Council - SUNA (Box 2, Folder 4)
  removed from 5139/box 56
- UTU - Members Time Book (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Stickers - UTU; Bumper Stickers - District 2, MEBA-AMO, AFL-CIO; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Broadsides removed from 5139/box 56 + 116 (see notes for details) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  What Your Brothers Say About Operation Redblock (2 copies); Who Really Gets Hurt When You Drink or Use Drugs on the Job? (3 copies); This Isn't What We Call Seeing The Light; Riding Tall On the Iron Horse Is High Enough; 5 copies of 'One Direction: Fo
- Pins/Buttons: Operation RedBlock -- UTU: It doesn't cost to belong - it pays (Box 4, Folder 1)
  pulled from 5139/box 83
- Key chains: Operation RedBlock (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Iron on patches: Operation RedBlock (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Stickers: Operation RedBlock -- Your Right to Drink Ends When My Shift Begins -- UTU (Box 4, Folder 4)
  pulled from 5139/box 76, 77
- Pins/buttons - Operation RedBlock: UTU (Box 4, Folder 5)
  pulled from 5139/box 78, 79
- Buttons and UTU Stickers (Box 4, Folder 6)
  pulled from 5139/box 90 and 91
- Misc. Memorabilia pulled from several boxes of collection 5139 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Stickers & business card - box 100; bumper sticker - box 106; membership card - box 100; stickers - box 109
- Buttons pulled from several boxes of 5139 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  7 - box 89; 1 - box 100; 2 - box 109
- Stamps {wood blocks with imprinted metal stamps): BL F&E; Round paper weight (Box 4, Folder 9)
  pulled from 5139/bx 110 - Paper weight - The Central Pacific and Union Pacific Railroads Linking the Nation-Promontory Summit, Utah / "The Pacific Railway is completed", May 10, 1869 [pulled from 5139/box 114
- Stickers (Box 4, Folder 10)
  pulled from 5139/bx 110
- Railroad scenes - copies of drawings done by D. Mahoney (Box 4, Folder 11)
  pulled from 5139/box 114
- Buttons - Operation Red Block (Box 4, Folder 12)
  pulled from 5139/box 116
- Operation Red Block - sew on patches (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Broadsides - UTU - dealing with Railroad drinking (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Buttons/Pins, stickers, patches, and plastic bag all labeled for the Operation RedBlock (Box 4, Folder 15)
  pulled form 5139/box 121